退下
Leave us.
查尔斯 请坐
Charles, please sit.
在我悼念爱妻期间
The factions and the fighting that went on inside this court.
宫廷内发生的朋党之争令我深恶痛绝
while I mourned were unacceptable.
我现任命你为枢密院议长及总务大臣
I am appointing you president of the council and lord great master.
我不在期间 所有大小事务皆由您负责
So in my absence, all will be answerable to you.
而非克伦威尔
not Cromwell.
是 陛下
Majesty.
同时指派爱德华·西摩
I am also appointing Edward Seymour to.
负责调查珀尔家族的活动
Investigate the activities of the Poles.
从现在起 他们都是嫌犯
From now on, they are all under suspicion.
你的家人还好吗
How's your family?
他们很好
They're well.
除了
Except…
我的妻子小产了
My wife lost the child she was carrying.
那我们俩都失去一些东西了
Then we have both lost something.
查尔斯 有时我想我快疯了
Oh, Charles, sometimes I think I shall go mad.
我的腿毒又发作了 疼痛难忍
My leg is poisoned and hurts again.
我真怕我儿子会死于瘟疫 每想至此我夜不能寐
I'm afraid that my son will die of the plague and I cannot sleep.
陛下 我知道我们都失去了什么
Majesty, I know what it is that we have both lost.
我们失去了我们的青春
We have lost our youth.
世上没有能够失而复得的东西
There's nothing in the world that can ever return it to us.
愿主你的名为万人所称颂
Benedictionem tuam domine, populus fidelis accipat.
阿门
Amen.
索尔兹伯里夫人
Lady salisbury.
饿了吧 吃吧
You're hungry, eat!
- 怎么回事 - 我不知道
- What's that? - I don't know.
索尔兹伯里夫人
Lady salisbury.
原谅我的无理
Forgive this intrusion,
但您和您的家人因涉嫌叛国
But you and these members of your family are arrested.
国王下令拘捕你们
By the king's orders on suspicion of treason,
你们必须都跟我走
You will all have to come straight with me.
不包括我的孙子吧 是吗
Not my grandson, surely?
所有人
All.
大使先生 我想与您私下谈谈
I wanted to talk to you in private, monsieur l'ambassadeur,
因为我有意迎娶一位法国新娘
Because I'm inclined towards a french bride.
尽管我的顾问大臣们认为我该结门皇室婚姻
Although my advisors think I should rather seek an imperial match.
我钦佩陛下的品味 厌恶那些顾问大臣们的多事
I admire your majesty's taste, and deplore that of your advisors.
可能是他们不通人情 不像您和我
Perhaps they are not men of the world, as we are.
我的掌玺大臣跟我提起有两名法国新娘人选
My lord privy seal spoke to me of two potential french brides.
玛丽亚 国王的女儿以及朗格维尔女士 吉斯的玛丽
Maria, the king's daughter, and marie de guise, madame de longueville.
自从我深入了解朗格维尔女士之后
Since I have heard further of madame de longueville,
我觉得她是妻子的不二之选
I cannot refrain from considering her as a wife.
好味道 桃子味
Good nose. peachy.
带点猫尿味 不是很甜
Cat's piss. not too sweet.
您听到些什么
What have you heard?
国王的女儿对我来说太年轻了
King's daughter is too young for me.
但朗格维尔女士就合适多了
But madame de longueville is much more suitable.
是个寡妇 已育有两个儿子 而且
Being herself a widow and having already borne two sons, and being,
听他们所说 十分丰满迷人
As they say, very… voluptuous.
我家主公告诉我说 若陛下能迎娶
My master told me that he would think it a great honor.
法国女子为新后 我们将荣幸之至
If your majesty were to take a french girl as your new wife.
我国女子任您挑选 除了朗格维尔女士
There is no lady who is not at his command, except madame de longueville,
她早和苏格兰王订下了婚约
Whose marriage to the king of scotland has already been arranged.
那也可以悔婚
That arrangement can be broken.
告诉你家主公 我可以付出
Tell your master that I can do twice as much for him as my nephew,
我那苏格兰王白痴外甥 所给予的双倍条件
The idiotic and beggarly scottish king.
是 但事实上
Yes… yes but, sir, in effect…
您就等于娶了他人的妻子
Then, you would be marrying another man's wife.
我只娶我中意的人
I will marry who I like.
卡斯特列先生 每个宫廷都给我提供了人选
Monsieur castillon, I have received offers from every court.
恕我进言 法王陛下提议两门婚事
Forgive me. But his majesty proposed a double marriage.
他19岁的儿子亨利迎娶您的女儿玛丽
His nineteen year old son Henry to your daughter Mary.
同时您可迎娶郎格维尔女士的姐妹之一
and one of madame de longueville's sisters to you.
她有两个姐妹 路易斯和里内
There are two of them, louise and renee.
法国宫廷盛传 前者
The former, remarkably for the french court,
仍是处子之身
Is rumored to be still a virgin.
太好吃了
Wonderful.
迎娶她 娶路易斯
Take her. take louise.
既然她还是个处女
Since she is still a maid,
您还可以亲自开垦这片处女地
You will have the advantage of shaping the passage to your measure.
我要见我的父亲
I want to see my father.
去把我的父亲找来
Go get my father!
我现在就要见我的父亲
I want my father now!
你知道我是谁 对吗
You know who I am, don't you?
是 我知道你是谁
Oh yes, I know who you are!
你是珀尔少爷
You're master pole!
他们说你将来会是英国国王
They say that some day you're going to be the king of england!
放开我 放手
Let go of me! Let go.
我们得来商讨一下我的婚事
We must discuss marriage.
法国人还是一如既往地令我难以下台
As usual, the french want to mess me around.
罗马皇帝提议什么人选
Who does the emperor propose?
陛下 罗马皇帝推举了克里斯蒂娜 他的外甥女
Your majesty, the emperor has put forward christina, his niece,
米兰公爵夫人
The duchess of Milan.
说说她的情况
Tell me about her.
她出生于丹麦 13岁嫁给米兰大公
Originally from denmark, she was married at thirteen to the duke of milan,
弗朗切斯科·斯福尔扎 公爵一年后去世
Francesco sforza, who died a year later.
她现年16岁 既是寡妇 又是处女
She is now sixteen, both a widow and, apparently, still a maid.
现居布鲁塞尔 同摄政者匈牙利的玛丽一起
She's living in brussels with the regent, Mary of Hungary.
据说她美貌无双
She is reported to be a great beauty,
最喜欢狩猎 玩牌
And likes nothing better than hunting and playing cards.
狩猎 玩牌
Hmm! hunting and playing cards?
我已经开始喜欢她了
I like her already.
派我们在荷兰的大使去作深入了解
Have our ambassador in the netherlands find out more about her.
是 陛下
Majesty.
大人 我国出使荷兰的大使 约翰·哈顿爵士到
My lord, our ambassador to the netherlands, sir john hutton.
约翰爵士
Sir john, i…
我有一迫切要务交由您处理
Have some most urgent business for you to do.
大人 瑞斯利先生已经告知我了
My lord, mr. risley has warned me.
你去准备陛下的妻子候选人名单
You are to make a list of potential candidates to share his majesty's bed.
大人
My lord…
我不谙挑选夫人之道
I have not much experience among ladies.
因此 此重任对我来说困难重重
Therefore, this commission to me is hard.
您要去布鲁塞尔
You are to go to Brussels.
您要去详细调查
You are to make particular enquiries there about christina,
克里斯蒂娜 米兰公爵夫人
christina Duchess of milan.
顺便
But while you are about it,
再行前往克里维斯公国
Go on to the duchy of cleves make enquiries.
调查公爵的二个姐妹 艾米利亚和安
There about the duke's two sisters amelia and anne.
我急切期望她们能列入候选名单
I am anxious that they should enter the reckoning.
是 克伦威尔大人
Yes, my lord cromwell.
我要见我的儿子 你把我的儿子怎么样了
I want to see my son. what have you done with my son?
- 我的儿子在哪儿 - 你儿子平安无事
- Where is my son? - your son is unharmed.
只要我们确定你们跟你的弟弟雷金纳德不同
He will remain unharmed until we are sure that you are not all traitors,
并非叛国贼 他就没事
Like your brother reginald.
你很清楚我们家族已经和雷金纳德脱离关系
You know very well that my family has disowned reginald.
我的母亲和我绝不纵容 也不会原谅他的所作所为
Neither my mother nor I supports or condones or what he has done!
我们公开宣示我们对陛下的忠诚拥护
We openly profess our allegiance to his gracious majesty!
我很欣赏我兄弟 红衣主教之所为
"i like well the proceeding of my brother, the cardinal.
嫌恶此王国内所行之举
"but I like not the doings of this realm,
我相信世道会发生变化
"and I trust to see a change of this world.
我真希望我们都在海外
"i would wish that we were both over the sea.
因为英格兰国已变得荒淫扭曲
"the world in england waxes all crooked; "
上帝的法律完全颠倒 修道院和教会都被推翻
The god's law has been turned upside down, abbeys and churches overthrown…"
谁给你那封信件
Who gave you that letter?
你否认这是你写的
Do you deny writing it?
国王他日必将暴毙
"the king will die one day suddenly.
他的坏腿将致他于死地 我们将会欢欣鼓舞
His leg will kill him, and we shall have jolly stirring."
你的宣誓效忠徒有其表 蒙塔古大人
Your professions of loyalty were all hollow, my lord montague.
毕竟 你是国王的表亲 金雀花王朝的后裔
You are, after all, the king's cousins, the last of the plantagenets.
白玫瑰家族的后人
The last of the white rose.
有人说你们波尔家族才是王朝的合法继承人
Some say you poles are the rightful heirs.
有朝一日必当皇冠加顶 是不是
"And will someday wear the garland." don't they?
弗朗西斯爵士
Sir francis.
陛下
Majesty.
我们现已找到对蒙塔古勋爵 亨利·珀尔不利的证据
Now that we found evidence against henry pole, lord montague,
我们还需找到指控他母亲的力证
We need something against the lady.
我要求你 有这般不忠不义儿子们
I ask you whether such dishonest and.
母亲又怎么能诚实
Treacherous sons could ever have had an honest mother.
那是谁
Who is that?
她是埃蒙特伯爵的遗孀
She's the widow of the earl of egmont.
一个寡妇
A widow?
且慢 她看来是不像 但已年过40
Wait. it's true she doesn't look it, but she's over forty.
但另一方面 宫廷内有一处女
On the other hand, there's a maid at court.
年仅14岁 但却凹凸有型
She's only fourteen but she already has a goodly stature.
水果成熟之前不要去采摘 弗朗西斯爵士
Let the fruit ripen before you pluck it, sir francis.
- 陛下 - 克伦威尔大人
- Majesty. - cromwell.
我刚收到约翰·哈顿爵士的函件
I have just received a letter from sir john hutton,
出使布鲁塞尔的大使
The ambassador in brussels.
他代表陛下前去问询调查
He's been making enquiries on your majesty's.
罗马皇帝的外甥女 米兰公爵夫人的情况
Behalf about the duchess of milan, the emperor's niece.
他说些什么
What does he say?
他写道
He writes,
不伦公爵夫人本人的美貌
"there is none in these parts for beauty of.
还是她的出身都无与伦比
Person "and birth to compare with the duchess.
她纯洁无邪一如故世的王后 愿上帝保佑她
"she is not so pure white as the last queen, and god pardon,
微笑的时候 她的脸颊和下巴上有两个酒窝
"but when she smiles, there appear two dimples "in her cheeks,
更添她的迷人
And one in her chin, which become her very well."
他还提到了其他女士吗
As he mentioned any other ladies?
只提到了克里维斯公爵的妹妹 安
Only a sister of the duke of cleves. anne.
- 他写道 - 我听说过她
- He writes - I've heard about her.
听说她一无是处 无论相貌还是人品
They say she is of no great praise, either of her personage or her beauty.
请原谅我 陛下 但
Forgive me, majesty, but…
但这个联姻有他的好处
On the other hand, such a match could have its advantages.
我国一直以来都得看
This realm has long been at the mercy of the.
罗马皇帝或法国的眼色行事
Machinations of the french or of the emperor.
克里维斯是新教同盟的成员之一
But cleves is a member of the protestant league,
其发展势力在欧洲不可小觑 足以与他们抗衡
Which daily grows in power across europe and could easily rival theirs.
因此 最后
Thus, at last…
英国终将不必仰他人鼻息
Could england make its own destiny.
尽管如此 我还是想多了解米兰公爵夫人
Even so, I am anxious to see more of the duchess of milan.
我想确定她是否真的如哈顿形容的那般貌美
I want to be sure she's as beautiful as hutton claims.
立刻派荷尔拜画师前去画像
Send master holbein to do a sketch of her by next tide.
- 是 陛下 - 克伦威尔大人
- Majesty. - master cromwell.
夫人 请您许可
With your permission, madam,
能否请问您 是否会考虑与我王联姻
May I ask if you would consider marrying the king?
您可以问 先生
You may ask, sir.
至于我的选择 您知道我听命于罗马皇帝陛下
And as for my inclination, you know I am at the emperor's command.
女士
Oh madam,
若您嫁给我家主公 您定会快乐无比
How happy you shall be if it be your chance to be matched with my master.
是吗 为什么
Shall i? why?
我家主公是世上最优雅的绅士
Oh, uh… my royal master is the most gentle gentleman that lives.
他和蔼可亲 平易近人
His nature is so benign and pleasant that till this day,
迄今为止 没有很多人 没有一个人听到他口出恶言
I think no man has heard many, if any angry words pass his mouth.
另一方面
On the other hand,
陛下三位王后的相继离世
Is it not strange that the king's majesty was in so little space.
这不奇怪吗
rid of his three queens?
有人怀疑其原配夫人 我的曾舅母 是被毒害
And they suspect that the first my great aunt was poisoned,
第二位无辜被处死
The second innocently put to death,
第三位因缺少照料而产后即死
And the third lost for lack of care in her childbed.
坦率地说 先生 如果我有两个脑袋
Frankly, sir, if I had two heads,
那么可以拿一个去服侍贵主上
Then one would be at his majesty's service.
可惜 我只有一个脑袋
Alas, I have only this one.
女士
Madam,
- 容我为我王申辩 他的良好品行 - 不用了
- Let me plead my master's better qualities and appeal to your heart. - no.
不劳您费心了 因为我不会改变心意
You must not labor any further, for I shall not fix my heart that way.
除非 罗马皇帝命令我服从
Unless, of course, the emperor commands me to.
女士
Oh, madam…
弗朗西斯爵士
Sir francis!
金雀花王朝旗帜
The royal banner of the plantagenets.
上帝 那里还会有什么
My god, what expectation is there?
这又是什么
What's this?
金雀花王家旗帜
The royal banner.
还有这个 在你的房子里发现的最有力的叛乱证据
And this, the most potent symbol of rebellion, discovered in your house.
先生 我只是个老妇
Sir, I am an old lady.
我没做任何错事或反叛国王陛下
I have done nothing wrong, or against the king's majesty.
你依然与你的儿子雷金纳德·珀尔有联络
You still communicate with your son reginald pole,
不顾他是叛贼
Despite him being a traitor.
无疑你在与他共谋新的叛乱
No doubt you plot new treacheries with him.
我这把年纪了 您怎么会这么想
How can you suppose that at my age,
我还有什么能力谋划叛乱
I am capable of plotting anything against anyone?
我只希望安享晚年 远离尘世
I wish only to live a quiet life, away from this world.
仁慈的国王能否发发慈悲 宽恕我们
If the king, in his mercy, could show pity and forgive us.
夫人 你们全家都被控犯下反叛陛下的叛国罪
Madam, you've all been attainted for high treason against his majesty.
证据对您极为不利
The evidence is great against you.
您还指望什么呢 您该好好乞求宽恕
For what you deserve, you may well beg mercy.
但天知道你是否会得到宽恕
But who shall say if it be granted or not?
祖母 您在哪里
Grandmother! where are you?
祖母
Grandmother!
米兰公爵夫人很迷人
The duchess of milan is enchanting.
甚合我意
I am singularly pleased.
此画使她看来很俏丽 也非常
This picture makes her very pretty. very…
充满活力
Full of life.
你可别想打她主意 查尔斯
Keep your hands off her, charles.
婚礼之后
After our wedding,
我们的小儿子将会册封为约克公爵
Our younger sons will be ennobled with the ancient dukedoms of york,
格洛斯特公爵 以及萨默塞特公爵
Gloucester and somerset.
届时玛丽公主就能与唐·路易丝亲王成婚
And princess mary can marry don luis.
这就是你要的吗 是不是 查尔斯
That's what you want, isn't it charles?
一场皇室联姻 正如当年沃尔西一直想让我娶一个法国新娘
An imperial wedding, just as wolsey always wanted a french one.
每人都自有谋划 我的需求无关紧要
Everyone has an agenda, and what I want doesn't matter!
珀尔家族有其谋划
All the poles have an agenda.
人们都在议论关在伦敦塔里的那
People talk about that poor little boy.
可怜的小男孩和老索尔兹伯里夫人
In the tower and poor old lady salisbury.
但让我告诉你 他们的血管里流动的是金雀花王朝的血
But let me tell you, they have plantagenet blood in their veins.
我父亲曾经告诫过我
And my father told me…
我父亲告诫过我 斩草不除根
My father told me that if you leave even a sapling in the ground,
春风吹又生
One day it will grow into a tree!
不久以后塔里那小男孩大旗一挥
And then that little boy in the tower will.
就可聚集4万军队
Have forty thousand troops flocking to his banners!
而你就尝尝这恶果吧
And you will be a sucker!
去把国王御医找来
Fetch the king's physician!
看在上帝份上 还不快跑
For god's sake, man. run!
查尔斯 查尔斯
Charles! charles!
大人 我必须要见陛下
My lord? I must see the king.
必须
Must?
就如我必须见您的外甥 王子 却被您挡驾了
Just as I must see your nephew, the prince, sometimes, but you prevent it.
国王卧病一个多星期了 音讯全无
The king has lain ill for over a week. there has been no news about him.
结果漫天谣言 甚至传言国王已死
So there are rumors. some say the king is dead.
这正合您意吧 是不是
That would suit you, wouldn't it?
- 这样您外甥就能做国王 - 他只是个孩子
- Since your nephew would be king. - he is a child.
那对任何人都没益处
That would be to no one's use.
对我不会 对你不会 对英格兰也不会
Not to mine, not to yours, and not to england's.
请您准许 公爵大人
With your permission, your grace,
我需要借此机会去反驳那些谣言
I would like the opportunity to disprove those rumors.
好吧
Very well.
以上帝的名义 这是怎么回事
What in the name of god…
这次他腿上的溃疡没能破裂
This time the ulcer on his leg has failed to burst,
以前都能破裂开
As it has always done before.
那就去请外科开刀师来切开溃疡
Then fetch the barber surgeons to lance it!
那样也许会使他丧命
That might kill him.
陛下情况如何
How is his majesty?
给王子加派双重卫兵
Double the guards around the prince.
不许任何人接近他 明白吗
No one is to be allowed access to him. do you understand?
是 大人
Yes, my lord.
让弗朗西丝爵士接管一队杭斯顿宫的守卫
Tell sir francis to take a detachment of the guard to hunsdon,
以使他们能以生命护卫玛丽公主的安全
So he and they may keep watch over the princess mary with their lives.
因为一旦国王驾崩 王子和她都各会有人拥立
For if the king dies, some will be for the boy, others for her.
是 公爵大人
Yes, your grace.
主啊
Oh lord…
万能的主
Lord…
我该怎么做
What shall I do?
克伦威尔先生 您曾提议启用外科开刀师
Mr. cromwell, I bid you call for the surgeon barbers.
我现准许此项要求
I will answer for it.
是 公爵大人
Yes, your grace.
陛下 请原谅我
Your majesty, forgive me.
孩子怎么样
How is the child?
他是世间最可爱 最漂亮的孩子
He is the sweetest, prettiest boy that ever lived.
确保他的安全
Keep him safe.
- 克伦威尔先生 - 陛下
- Mr. cromwell. - majesty.
您最近与卡斯特列沟通过吗
Have you spoken to castillon recently?
有 陛下
Yes, majesty.
关于郎格维尔女士的事他说了些什么
What did he say about madame de longueville?
她 已经与苏格兰王结婚了
She has already got married to the king of scotland.
她会后悔的
She'll regret it.
只要她见识了那里的鬼天气
When she sees what the weather is like up there.
大使先生提到法王弗朗西斯的另外两个表亲
The ambassador mentioned there are two other cousins of king francis potentially.
可供陛下选择
available to your majesty.
凡尔登的玛丽和维恩的安
Marie de vendome and anne of lorraine.
当然了
Apparently,
凡尔登的玛丽已宣布她有意做修女
Marie de vendome has already announced her intention to become a nun,
但卡斯特列认为这不成问题
Although castillon thought that not necessarily an obstacle.
真的非常法式
How very french.
我需要画像 明白吗
I need pictures. do you understand?
我需要看到她们
I need to see them.
我得看看将陪伴我余生的女人是什么样子
I need to see the woman who is going to be my companion for life.
同米兰公爵夫人的协商进行的如何了
What of the negotiations with the duchess of milan?
姻亲关系存在问题
There is the problem of affinity.
作为罗马皇帝的侄女
As niece to the emperor,
公爵夫人就是阿拉贡凯瑟琳的孙甥女
The duchess is therefore great niece to katherine of aragon.
在过去
In the past,
这种问题可通过教皇特许来解决
Such obstacles might have been overcome by papal dispensation.
那么现在此事就不成问题了
Well, there is no question of that now.
但或许 作为英国教会的领袖
But perhaps, as head of the church of england,
罗马皇帝可以容我来发布特许
The emperor will allow me to make a dispensation.
是的 陛下 自然如此
Yes, majesty. naturally.
得要个可人儿才能唤起我的恋爱之心
It will take a good sport to make me feel amorous again.
我以为你丈夫警告过你远离我
I thought your husband warned you to stay away from me.
他确实警告过 但现在他不可不关心这个
He did. but now he doesn't care.
他说他不屑杀了你
He said he couldn't be bothered to kill you.
知道吗 由于对你丈夫所知甚少 我越对他有兴趣
You know, the less I know about your husband the more he fascinates me.
我多少了解点多数人的立场
I know, more or less, where most people stand…
像萨福克 克伦威尔
Like suffolk, cromwell…
纵然他们努力掩饰 我也知道他们的所思所想
I know their true beliefs, even if they try to hide them.
而爱德华 谁知道他内心真正的信仰
But edward, who knows what he truly believes?
- 要不要我来告诉你呢 - 作为我服务的报酬
- Would you like me to tell you? - for services rendered!
你可没你自己想的那么棒
You're not quite as good as you think you are.
但还是很棒的 告诉我
That's still pretty good. tell me.
他只信他自己
He believes in himself.
在他的命运里
In his destiny.
爱德华王子才是通往他天命的钥匙
Prince edward is the key to his destiny.
没有什么挡得了他的路
Nothing will stand in his way.
他是个改革者
He's a reformer?
不 说吧 我也是呢 我发誓
No, you can answer. I am too, I swear.
人人都知道我对天主教派深恶痛绝
Everyone knows I hate popery with a passion.
所以有时他们才会叫我耶稣会教长
That's why sometimes they call me the black pope.
你好 我刚被教皇搞过
Hello! I've just been fucked by the pope!
奉圣父圣子及圣神之名
E nomine patri, et filii e spiritus sancti.
他是怎么看克伦威尔的
How does he think about cromwell?
这我不知道
That I don't know.
不过
But…
有人抓到射杀罗伯特·帕金顿议员的凶手了吗
Did anyone ever discover who shot robert packington, mp?
我虽然行过死阴的幽谷 也不怕遭害 因为你与我同在
Si ambulem in mediio umbrae mortis, non timebo mala.
阿门
Amen.
蒙塔古大人 我是来帮您去往美好之地
My lord montague, I am here to help you to a better place.
你们知道我是无辜的 你们这群杂种
You know I'm not guilty, you bastard.
我的兄弟才有罪 但你们却碰不了他
Only my brother is guilty, but you can't touch him, can you?
所以只能滥杀无辜来交差
So you have to kill the innocent.
你的罪行已确认无误
Your guilt has been established beyond question.
在这个国度 过去曾有规程
There used to be procedures here,
完善的法律程序
Proper legal procedures in this country.
判定谁有罪 谁无罪
To establish who is guilty and who is not!
但现在都没有了
But that's all gone now.
你们甚至都无需进行审判
You don't even have to have a trial…
所以既然没了司法制度 剩下的唯有暴政了
So since there is no judiciary, what's left is only tyranny.
我母亲在哪
Where is my mother?
索尔兹伯里夫人就在这儿 在塔里
Lady salisbury is here, within the tower.
请好好关照她 主教大人
Please have a care for her, my lord bishop.
无论她做了什么冒犯您的事
Whatever she may have done, be it so offensive,
她已是个年迈忠诚的老妇了
She is an old and true woman,
毕生都遵循上帝的教导
And has always lived under the precepts of god.
我会好生照料着她的
I will have a tender care for her.
全心全意 大人
Body and soul, my lord.
相信我
Trust me.
你知道的 大人
You know, my lord…
这是个事实
This is the truth.
国王从未成就过人 但他会一再毁灭人
The king never made a man, but he destroyed him again.
所以小心行事吧 大人
So take good care, my lord.
走吧
Come along.
比起其他人 我更喜欢这些法国女孩的长相
I like the look of some of these french girls more than others.
但画像可信吗
But can the likeness be trusted?
这些画家美化人物不是奉承这些女士
Could the artist be not using some lies to either.
就是取悦我 即使荷尔拜也不例外
Flatter the lady or please me? even master holbein?
没见过她们真人要我怎么决定
How can I make a decision on these girls when I haven't met them in flesh?
- 去跟卡斯特列谈谈 - 遵命陛下
- Talk to castillon. - majesty.
陛下是否能再次考虑
If your majesty might still choose to consider the.
单纯但又魅力无限的克里维斯的安
Simple but profound charms of anne of cleves or of.
或是她的姐妹呢
Her sister,
同这个基督教国家结盟
And of the benefits to you.
陛下您和我国颇能从中受益
and to this realm of a new alignment with the protestant league?
温彻斯特主教大人觐见
His grace the bishop of winchester.
- 主教大人 - 陛下
- My lord bishop. - majesty.
陛下
Your majesty,
请原谅我的突然拜访 但我注意到某些新教徒
Forgive me but it has come to my attention that certain evangelicals are still.
仍在布道说教 公然反对教义六条款
Preaching against the six articles of faith.
和陛下的宗教教义
and your majesty's religious agreement.
约翰·兰伯特先生也是其中之一
Mr.John lambert is one such,
他一星期在伦敦面向广大民众做一次布道
Who preaches once a week in london to large audiences.
兰伯特先生拒绝承认圣餐仪式中圣体的真实存在
Mr.Lambert denies the real presence of god in the sacrament of communion,
反而说这仅仅是
Saying rather that it is merely a…
耶稣受难的象征性纪念
Symbolic commemoration of the passion christ.
那么兰伯特先生会因耶稣的原话被判有罪 祂说
Then mr.Lambert will be condemned in christ's own words, who said,
这是我的身体
"this is my body".
他要么放弃信仰要么被处火刑 我是不会庇护异教徒的
He will recant or be burned; I will not patron heretics.
还有事吗
Is there more?
也许这不关我的事 陛下 但我听说
Perhaps it is none of my business, your majesty, but I am told that.
兰伯特先生和克伦威尔大人关系很好
Mr.Lambert is well known to my lord cromwell.
他们似乎曾一起在剑桥接受教育
It appears that they were educated together at cambridge.
六个月前
Then some six months ago,
兰伯特因涉嫌进行异教宣传而被逮捕
When lambert was apprehended on suspicion of promoting religious heresy,
克伦威尔大人撤回了此项指控
My lord cromwell had the charges dismissed.
谢谢 主教大人
Thank you, my lord bishop.
国王同米兰公爵夫人的联姻进展得怎样
What news of the king's marriage to the duchess of milan?
唉 公主 我认为这是不太可能成功的
Alas, princess, I think it is not to happen.
公爵夫人是您母亲的孙外甥女
The duchess is the great niece of your mother,
姻亲关系太紧密了
And so the affinity is too touching.
同时我也觉得那位夫人并不想嫁给国王
Also, I think the lady does not want to marry the king.
那么 我也不能嫁给唐路易斯了吗
Then… I shall not marry don luis?
他们说国王现在有可能会娶个法国小姐
They say the king may now marry a french lady.
而您会许配给法国国王的某个儿子
And you one of the french king's sons.
这显然不合您意吧
Surely that would not please you.
只要您欢喜 我的小姐 我就欢喜
Anything would please me, my lady, which made you happy.
只怕我生来就得不到幸福 阁下
I am afraid I was not born for happiness, excellency.
我听说索尔兹伯里夫人还被囚禁在塔楼内
I hear lady salisbury is been kept in the tower.
她儿子已经被处决了
and her son executed.
确实令人唏嘘
It is sadly so.
她的孙子也成了阶下囚
Her grandson too is being kept a prisoner.
这肯定都是克伦威尔干的好事
I am sure it is all cromwell's doing.
这话我不可以对别人说 阁下 但我可以对你说
I should not say this to many people, excellency, but I say it to you,
即我很同意他是撒旦使者的说法
That I agree with those who say he is messenger of satan.
我发誓他毒害了国王的心智
I swear he has poisoned the king's mind.
如果我可以 我会把他从国王身边拖走 然后烧死他
And if I could, I would strip him from the king's side and burn him.
法国大使阁下觐见
His excellency, the french ambassador.
- 卡斯特列先生 - 陛下
- Monsieur castillon. - majesty.
我们已比较了现有所有候选人选
We have been considering all these candidates for our hand.
- 有好多呢 - 的确
- There are so many. - indeed.
一大群温文尔雅的女士
A warren of honorable ladies.
不错
Quite.
但事实上 在此等情况下
But the fact is, in the circumstances,
因为她们个个如此迷人
Because so many of them appear attractive,
我不知如何才能单独召见她们
I do not see how I can approach them individually.
因此
So…
弗朗西斯国王能否安排七到八个到加来
Perhaps king francis can assemble seven or eight of them at calais,
然后我可以去那里 一起见面接触一下
Then I could go there and make their acquaintances all at the same time…
不 法国没有派送贵族小姐的惯例
No. It is not a french custom to send ladies of that rank,
尤其这些女士都来自最高贵的王侯贵族
Of such noble and princely families,
更别说送去候选 如同出售马匹一般
To be passed in review as if they were prize horses…
如果陛下看中了某位女士
Perhaps if your majesty desires one of these ladies,
也许可以按传统做法
You could send an envoy to report on her manner and appearance?
派一名使节向您汇报她的仪态外貌
In the traditional way.
我只相信自己
I trust no one but myself.
此事事关己身
The thing touches me too near.
我要在作出决定前 看到并了解她们
I want to see and know them before deciding.
也许陛下想一个个品尝过来
Maybe your majesty would like to mount them one after another,
然后选个最上手的
And then pick the one you find best broken in?
卡斯特列先生
Monsieur castillon.
你有十秒钟时间离开我的宫殿
You have ten seconds to get out of my court,
否则我会打的你满地找牙
Or I will beat you like the dog that you are.
- 克伦威尔先生 - 陛下
- Mr. cromwell. - majesty.
有个无药可救的异教徒叫约翰·兰伯特
An incorrigible heretic called john lambert is now.
正囚禁在塔楼内 可能快处以火刑了
Imprisoned in the tower and likely soon to be burned.
我相信你认识这个人
I believe you know this man.
许多年前 我在剑桥的时候认识他
I knew him, many years ago. at cambridge.
之后就不联络了
Not since?
据我所知没有 陛下
Not to my knowledge, your majesty.
当你们一起在剑桥时
And whilst you were at cambridge together,
你跟他有什么志同道合的观点吗
Did you share some of his opinions?
说说 克伦威尔先生 你现在到底信仰什么
Tell me, mr. cromwell, what do you believe now.
天地为证 陛下 我信仰陛下的信仰
As the world stands, your majesty, I believe what you believe.
那么你也同意他理该被烧死
So you think it right that he should be burned?
是的 除非他放弃信仰
Yes. unless he recants.
是的
Yes.
我差点儿忘了
Oh, I forgot.
- 她们的名字叫什么来着 - 什么
- What were their names again? - majesty?
克里维斯公爵的两个姐妹
The sisters of the duke of cleves.
艾米利亚和安
Amelia and anne.
Amelia and anne…
派人去了解下她们
Send someone to take a look at them.
- 我们可能要退而求其次了 - 是的 陛下
- We'll have a second opinion. - majesty.
天鹅宫 克里夫斯 德国
Swan Castle, Cleves, Germany.
威廉姆公爵现在接见你们
Duke william will receive you now.
殿下
Your highness.
英国使者觐见
The english envoys.
- 先生们 - 殿下
- Gentlemen. - your highness.
这么说亨利国王需要个妻子
So his majesty king henry needs a wife,
他对我的妹妹们感兴趣
And he is interested in my sisters?
是 陛下听闻她们性情温和
Yes, His majesty has been persuaded of their.
很符合皇室配偶的标准
Amiability and of their suitability as royal consorts.
尤其是安 年长的那位
Especially anne, the eldest,
陛下闻知这位小姐颇受好评
Who has been much praised in the king's hearing.
我并不感到惊奇
I am not surprised.
陛下也提议将他的女儿玛丽
His majesty would also propose the.
许配给您的长子
Marriage of his daughter mary to your eldest son; a.
这将会是一场新教徒的联盟
Liaison with the protestant league,
还有为他的军队征集数百位善战的炮手
And the recruitment of a hundred seasoned cannoneers for his army.
如此说来 先生们 我们还有很多事要商讨
There is, then, gentlemen, much to discuss.
确实如此 但首先请允许我们 见见您的妹妹们
Indeed. but first, we should like your permission to meet your sisters.
为什么
Why?
国王要求我们据亲眼所见如实汇报
The king will expect us to report back on what we have seen.
如果没亲眼见到这些女士 国王会不高兴的
To say that we have not seen the ladies would not exactly please him.
他同时要求我们带回一副安的肖像
He has also asked for a portrait of anne to be sent back to him.
真不巧 我的宫廷画师克兰纳克先生身体抱恙
Unfortunately, my court painter mr. crananch is ill and indisposed.
既然如此 我们可以派世人敬仰的艺术家荷尔拜先生
In that case, we can send over mr. holbein, who is an admirable artist.
确实
Indeed.
是的 也许吧
Yes, perhaps.
但你们进行得太快了吧
But you are going too quickly.
你们以为我的国家是什么 肉市吗
What do you think my country is? a meat market?
我会安排大臣们商讨此事
I will arrange with my chancellor for negotiations to commence,
到了一定阶段 你们可以有机会
And you may have the opportunity, at some stage,
引荐给我的妹妹们
Of being presented to my sisters.
- 殿下 我们 - 我们会再见面的
- Your highness, - we will meet again.
日安了 先生们
Good day, gentlemen.
约翰
John…
托马斯
Thomas.
见到你真好
How good to see you.
你在宫里干得真不错
And how excellently you have done in the world.
真希望我们的重逢能在更好的地方
I could wish our reunion was in some better place.
我很快就能离开这个地方
I shall be quit of this place soon enough.
然后去往一个更美好的世界
And on my way to a far better place.
约翰 你没必要去死
John, you do not have to die.
你只需要投其所好 在献祭仪式后
All you have to say to satisfy the king is that, after consecration,
宣称圣饼和红酒确实是耶稣的真体和血液
The wafer and wine are truly the body and blood of christ.
但你我明知它们不是
But you and I know that they are not.
你不用相信 你只要说出来就行了
You don't have to believe it, you just have to say it.
托马斯
Ah, thomas…
我终于明白一个人在俗世中获得成功要付出什么代价
I see now what it takes for a man to make his way in this world.
他必须伪善
He must make a practice of hypocrisy.
谨慎行事并没有坏处
There is no harm in discretion.
相信我
And believe me,
我想免去你即将面临的苦难
I want to spare you the awful pains which have been prepared for you.
托马斯 耶稣不也承受了巨大的苦难
Did christ himself not suffer awful pains, thomas?
我们不需要殉道者
We do not need martyrs.
我们需要活生生的人
We need living men who will go on about.
这样才能慢慢开展我们的改革
Quietly spreading the business of our reformation.
如果我在这么基础的问题上动摇了
But who will believe a word I say if I.
那么谁还会相信我所说的话呢
Alter my opinion on such a fundamental thing?
约翰 我再问你一次 我至少能给你个自由的选择
John, I say to you again, while at least I have a free choice.
你想死还是活
will you live or die?
亲爱的克伦威尔大人
My dear lord cromwell,
我发觉此刻我们谈论的并不是我 而是你
I see that all this while we have not been talking about me but about you.
不是我的良心 而是你的良心
Not about my poor conscience but about yours.
我看到你害怕承担连带责任
I see that you are afraid of guilt by association,
甚至期待我欺骗自己的灵魂
And would rather I perjured my own soul.
可惜 这是我在世间所剩的唯一的东西
Alas, it is the only thing in the world I have left.
你不愿自救我感到很遗憾
I am sorry you choose not to save yourself.
叛徒们 退后
Get back you rebel!
以国王的名义 你们都退后
Get back in the name of the king!
我会为你祈祷的
I'll pray for you.
为耶稣献身 为耶稣献身
All for christ! all for christ!
陛下
Majesty.
兰伯特先生施刑完毕
Mr. lambert has gone to his execution.
并且下地狱了
And to hell.
玛丽公主请求您放索尔兹伯里女士一条生路
Princess mary begs you to spare the life of lady salisbury,
她说 她就如同她母亲一般
who, she says, was like a mother to her.
她也是雷金纳德·珀尔的母亲 那人连上帝也不会原谅
She was also a mother to reginald pole, whom even heaven can't forgive.
威廉姆公爵称他的画师病了
Duke william says that his painter is ill,
他不能提供她妹妹安的画像
He cannot furnish images of his sister anne.
派荷尔拜去
Send holbein.
我一定要看到她的画像
I must see her image.
- 陛下 - 克伦威尔先生
- Majesty. - mr. cromwell.
先生们
Gentlemen.
我容许你们一睹我妹妹们的芳容
You have my permission to look upon my sisters.
殿下 我们甚至不能分辨谁是安谁是艾米利亚
Your highness, we cannot even tell which is anne and which amelia.
- 先生们 我是安 - 我是艾米利亚 大人们
- Sirs, I am anne. - and I am amelia, your honors.
殿下
Your highness.
根据我们的目的 这样可不行
For our purposes, this is no good.
不行 什么 难道你们要看她们裸体吗
No good? what? would you see them naked?
难道您不祷告吗 夫人
Have you not been praying, lady?
您现在就要被砍头了
Your head is going to be cut off now.
我不想死 我不想死
I don't want to die. I don't want to die.
不 求求你 不要伤害我 求你 不要 不要
No, please don't hurt me. please, no. don't! don't! don't!
别伤害我 我还不想死 我还不想死
Don't hurt me! I don't want to die! I don't want to die!
不要 不要杀死我 不要
No! don't kill me! no!
上帝救我啊 上帝救我啊
God save me! god help me!
看在上帝的份上 留点尊严吧
For god's sake, have some dignity.
不 我还不想死
No! I don't want to die!
- 主教阁下 - 我的孩子
- Eminence… - my child.
- 我可怜的孩子 - 他杀了他们
- My poor child. - he's killed them!
我的哥哥 还有我可怜的母亲 耶稣啊
My brother! my poor mother! oh, jesus! jesus!
英国国王是最残酷最让人憎恶的暴君
The king of england is the most cruel and abominable tyrant.
毫无疑问 他应该被武力推翻
There's no doubt now, he must be overthrown by force.
比起永世遭受臣民的诅咒
Better that he should die,
他还不如现在就死
Than risk the eternal damnation of all his subjects.
但我们无能为力
But there's nothing we can do.
我们可以
But we can.
教皇陛下准备宣布将他逐出教会
His holiness is ready to promulgate the bull of excommunication.
罗马和法国已经建交
The emperor and the french have made peace and they.
他们都愿意向英国宣战
Are now both willing to point their swords at england.
他们会撤出他们的大使 并准备战舰开始进攻
They will withdraw their ambassadors and prepare a fleet for invasion.
教皇希望你回到荷兰和法国
And the holy father expects you to return to the.
去协助他们的准备工作
Netherlands and to france to assist their preparations.
不 不 求你
No. no, please…
让我用别德方法来帮忙吧
Let me help in other ways.
什么 说说看 难道你害怕了
What? tell me. are you frightened?
你应该感谢上帝召你家人到天堂
You should thank god that he has called your family to heaven.
你不应该哭泣
You should not weep.
如果不顺从上帝 不顺从上帝的旨意还算什么信仰
What is belief if not belief in the will of god?
难道你认为教皇派你去荷兰
Do you think the holy father wants you.
是为了他自己的利益
To go to the netherlands for his own sake?
你难道不认为他先请示过上帝吗
Don't you think he has asked god for guidance?
原谅我
Forgive me.
年轻的时候 我在德国担任牧师
When I was a young priest in germany,
我家被路德教会雇佣兵占领
My family's house was occupied by lutheran mercenaries.
我有个漂亮的妹妹
I had a beautiful sister,
我爱她胜过世间一切
Whom I loved more than anything else in the world.
也许 甚至比爱上帝更多
And perhaps even more than god.
他们强奸了她 然后切下她的双乳
Well, they raped her, they cut off her breasts,
他们当着我的面 把她的碎尸拿去喂狗
They threw pieces of her to their dogs, right in front of my eyes.
每个人都有自己的重担 珀尔红衣主教
All of us have burdens to carry, cardinal pole.
过来吧 珀尔大人
Come along now, master pole.
我说过 珀尔红衣主教
There you are, cardinal pole.
该是你痛不欲生的时候了
Now eat your heart.